Preliminary Guide to the Fashion and Costume Plate Collection
Yale University Arts Library
Fashion and costume plate collection
1700-1900
DRA 5
Yale University Arts Library
1.5
(6 boxes)
The collection consists of plates, scrapbooks, and dress pattern catalogs, depicting European and American fashion, costume, and national dress primarily from the 18th and 19th centuries.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The collection consists of plates collected by the Drama Library and the Arts of the Book Collection over many years. Scrapbooks were the gift of Mrs. Bertram W. Martus to the Drama Library, 1960.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Scope and Contents
The collection consists of fashion plates from British, American, and French publications dating from the 18th through 19th centuries, including Gallery of Fashion and Modes de Paris; 19th century plates depicting national dress of individuals from various social classes and professions including Italian, Swiss, and Eastern European; plates depicting 18th century French theatrical personalities in popular roles; several 19th century American dress pattern catalogs by Butterick and McCall's; and scrapbooks containing a variety of fashion, national dress, and theatrical plates dating from the 19th century.
Arrangement
Preliminarily arranged by type and by nationality.
Actors -- France; Clothing and dress; Costume; Fashion plates
- Individual Plates
  - Fashion – 18th and 19th century
    - American
      - Frank Leslie's Monthly Magazine, 1861 (Box 1)
      - Peterson's Magazine, 1866-1867 1875 (Box 1)
      - Miscellaneous, circa 1800-1899 (Box 1)
    - British
      - Gallery of Fashion, 1794-1797 (Box 1)
    - French
      - Costumes Parisiens, 1828-1830 (Box 1)
      - Modes de Paris, 1828-1830 (Box 1)
      - Moniteur des Dames et des Demoiselles, [18--] (Box 1)
      - Société des Journaux de Modes Réunis, [18--] (Box 1)
      - Miscellaneous, circa 1800-1899 (Box 1)
  - National Dress
    - Denmark, Netherlands, England, Wales, circa 1700-1899 (Box 2)
    - France, circa 1400-1499 circa 1600-1799 (Box 2)
    - Italy, circa 1700-1799 (Box 2)
    - Switzerland, circa 1800-1899 (Box 2)
    - Northern and Eastern Europe, circa 1700-1899 (Box 6)
    - Various European countries (predominantly Eastern Europe), circa 1700-1899 (Box 2)
    - Military dress of various European countries, circa 1700-1899 (Box 6)
  - Theatrical Costume
    - French
      - Actors (A-V), circa 1800-1899 (Box 3)
      - Actresses (A-V), unidentified, circa 1800-1899 (Box 3)
- Dress Pattern Catalogs
  - American
    - Butterick (originals and photostatic copies), 1886 1887 (Box 3)
    - McCall's (originals and photostatic copies), 1886 (Box 3)
- Scrapbooks
  Scope and Contents
  Five scrapbooks containing French and German national dress, costume, dance, theatrical, and fashion plates from various published sources.
  - Scrapbooks, circa 1800-1899 (Box 4)
  - Scrapbooks, circa 1800-1899 (Box 5)